Guide to the Leland Stanford, Jr., Collection SC0033C
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Leland Stanford, Jr., collection
1870-1999
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford, Leland
SC0033C
2.5 Linear Feet
Scope and Content
Correspondence, journal, notebooks, drawings, personality studies, and school work of Leland Jr., and condolences to Senator and Mrs. Stanford regarding the death of their son. The correspondence and journal relate primarily to family travels in Europe and activities at home in San Francisco and Palo Alto, to his interests in archeology and collecting, and to his education. The collection also includes correspondence between Jane Lathrop Stanford and William T. Ross, one of Leland Jr.'s tutors.
Biography
Leland Stanford, Jr., the only child of Senator and Mrs. Leland Stanford, was born in Sacramento, California on May 14, 1868. His early death in March 1884 just before his sixteenth birthday inspired the founding of Leland Stanford Junior University in 1885.
Provenance
Gifts of Jane Lathrop Stanford, Thomas Welton Stanford, David Starr Jordan, Helen Stanford Canfield, David H. Canfield, and others; also includes purchases.
Access Restrictions
None.
United States -- Pictorial works. -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Stanford, Leland; Stanford, Leland; Stanford, Leland; Burdette, Robert Jones.; Ross, William T., 1942-; Stanford, Jane Lathrop; Cesnola, Luigi Parma di
- Leland Stanford, Jr. papers, 1870-1999; 1870-1884; Series 1
  - Outgoing correspondence, 1879-1883 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - to J. T. Wilson, wants small boiler for stationary engine, undated
    - to Mr. Wilson re railroad car, laying track, 1879 June 19
    - to Harry Farrington, Jr., re railroad on Palo Alto estate, 1879 June 20
    - to Wilson Taylor ("Friend Wilsy") re snow ball fights with Wellington on Sierra Nevada trip, 1879 Oct 21
    - to Wilse re "Kearny is raising the Dickens out West," bicycling in Albany, NY, visit to "penitentiary", 1880 Feb 29
    - to Friend "Wiltsy" re Albany bicycle club, dog "Cootsey", 1880 Mar 30
    - to Leland Stanford re Berlin, "Dom Cathedral," royalty, Markat painting, 1880 Nov 8
    - (Nice, France) to Leland Stanford re silk factory in Lyons, making velvet, 1880 Dec 19
  - Outgoing correspondence, 1881-1882 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - to Leland Stanford re Rome sightseeing, 1881 Mar 13
    - to Mrs. Dyer Lathrop re Rome, King's birthday, audience with Pope (with cover), 1881 Mar 14
    - Leland Stanford re visit to Pompeii, excavations there, going to Vesuvius tomorrow, 1881 Mar 19 to
    - (Frankfurt) to Aunt Kate re autumn military maneuvers in Hamburg, 1881 Sep 28
    - to Joey Stanford re prescription for paint for engine, photo (with cover), 1882 Nov 9
    - to Friend Wilsie re mechanical troubles on RR trip to San Diego, 1882 Nov 10
    - to Friend Wilsie re New York theater, Timothy Hopkins wedding, please check on puppies and horses, 1882 Dec 5
  - Outgoing correspondence, 1883 Jan-Jun (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - to Wilsey wants news of puppies, sick with a cold, troubles with horses and carriages in New York City ALS, (mss copy and typescript copy), 1883 Jan 16
    - to "Joe" [Josiah Winslow Stanford ?] re steam boat and steam engines, with sketches, 1883 Jan 23
    - (New York) to Wilsie re Union League Club fire, 1883 Feb 15
    - to Wilsie re his London address, 1883 May 24
    - to Aunt Kate re R. M. S. "Germanie" voyage, Leland and Jane Stanford ill, wants news of his dog Toots, 1883 June 2
    - to Miss Hull re London, Jane and Leland Stanford ill, have had only one row, 1883 June 15
    - to Wilsie re London sightseeing, 1883 June 25
  - Outgoing correspondence, 1883 Jul-Aug 16 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - to Aunt Kate re bicycles, future machine shop at home, London sightseeing, 1883 July 2
    - to Uncle Ariel asking to have his things looked after, 1883 July 9
    - (Paris) to Aunt Kate re Jane Stanford's illness, 1883 Aug 2
    - (Le Havre) to Leland Stanford re life in their hotel, taking German lessons, 1883 Aug 9
    - (Le Havre) to Leland Stanford re drunk coachman fell of the box, hired his own phaeton and horse, lessons, 1883 Aug 15
    - (Le Havre) to Leland Stanford re Jane Stanford's health, Miss Hart here to keep her company, 1883 Aug 16
  - Outgoing correspondence, 1883 Aug 19-31 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - (Le Havre) to Leland Stanford re Jane Stanford better, he's still swimming, 1883 Aug 19
    - (Le Havre) to Leland Stanford re Jane Stanford's health, leaving next week, 1883 Aug 21
    - (Le Havre) to Leland Stanford re Jane Stanford improving, he goes 5 miles to get her milk from local farm, 1883 Aug 22
    - (Le Havre) to Leland Stanford re Jane Stanford's birthday, weather hot, 1883 Aug 25
    - (Le Havre) to Leland Stanford re Jane Stanford's health, Dr. stopped the mercury treatments, 1883 Aug 28
    - (Le Havre) to Leland Stanford re delayed leaving to visit with Tillotsons, 1883 Aug 31
  - Outgoing correspondence, 1883 Sep 2-9 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - (Paris) to Leland Stanford re arrived in Paris, went to Hippodrome, attended fete for the poor in Tuilleries, 1883 Sep 2
    - (Paris) to Miss Hull re getting along moderately in his lessons, dog Toots in California has become a vagabond, Jane Stanford enjoyed her birthday card, 1883 Sep 2
    - (Paris) to Leland Stanford re he and Jane attending theater last night, 1883 Sep 4
    - (Paris) to Leland Stanford re thinks Jane would recover better in Palo Alto, taking German and gymnastic lessons, 1883 Sep 7
    - to Leland Stanford re taking drive in "Bois" and going to theater, would like to go to Homburg, 1883 Sep 9 Paris
  - Outgoing correspondence, 1883 Sep 12-1884 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - (Paris) to Leland Stanford re buying things for museum, 1883 Sep 12
    - (Paris) to Leland Stanford re Jane Stanford's health worse, couldn't do proposed trip to Constantinople, 1883 Sep 14
    - (Paris) to Uncle Ariel re trip to Bordeaux to see Wine Making at Chateau La Fette, glad to hear of success of horses, 1883 Oct 17
    - (Vienna) to Aunt Kate re cities and sights so far, not all the houses were put on map of the farm, to dine with Mr. Taft the American Minister, 1883 Dec 25
    - (Naples) to Miss Hull re Christmas in Vienna, crossing Danube on ice, Constantinople meeting with Sultan's Aide-de-camp, met Schliemann in Athens, 1884 Feb 11
  - Incoming correspondence, 1870-1883 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - L. B. di Cesnola to Sir Philip Cunliffe Owens introducing Leland Stanford Jr., 1883 Sep 22
    - Lizzie Hull re her activities in Chicago, his arguments with Mr. Nash, 1883 July 4
    - Wm. Sherman re acquiring C. P. medal, 1870 May 10
    - Leland Stanford re meeting in Homburg, his health, 1883 Aug 21; [photocopy; original in SC33a]
    - Leland Stanford re his health, 1883 Aug 30; [photocopy; original in SC33a]
    - Leland Stanford re bad weather in Homburg, soon they will all be heading home to Palo Alto, 1883 Sep 9; [photocopy; original in SC33a]
    - Wilson G. Taylor, birthday card, 1882 May 12
    - Wilson G. Taylor re Leland's dogs and horse, likes his dog cart, snow storm in San Francisco, 1883 Jan 25
    - Wilson G. Taylor re Leland's dog sick, art school, 1883 Oct 16
    - Wilson G. Taylor re snow, being in art school and his plans to study in Europe, undated
    - Woodbury & Haley re Leland Jr. and Mr. Nash attending Heald's Business College, 1882 June 22
    - Frank [?] re leaving business for college, hopes to hear from him soon, Mar 30 1882?
  - Workbook, German lessons, French lessons, doodling, stamps, description of Colosseum, Pompeii, handwriting practice, circa 1880-81 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Cash accounts, 1881 Jul 27-Oct 19 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Logbook from European trip, 1881 Apr 17-Aug 10 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Scope and Contents note
    Entries include remarks on way of life, arrival of Mr. Nash (new teacher), father sitting for Meissonnier, assassination of President Garfield. Handwriting varies, some entries possibly written by Nash.
  - Workbook German lessons (mostly blank), 1883: (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Birth certificate (notarized statement re date and time of his birth dated, July 12, 1898) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Fowler, O. S. "Phrenological Character of Master Stanford,", Dec 29, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Stanton, Mary Olmsted, Scientific Physiognomist, "Delineation of the Character of Leland Stanford, Jr., From a Photo-portrait taken at the age of 14 yrs. & 10 mos.,", undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Clipping re Leland's Christmas reception held in San Francisco, 1877 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Memorabilia: invitation and dance card from 1877 party; blank greeting card (?), nd. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Memorabilia: calling card for Leland D. Stanford (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Memorabilia: tourist guide to Edinburgh, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Memorabilia: cards with pictures of ships (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Memorabilia: fragment of printed Latin map of Italy and ms. note (indecipherable) [apparently found in his bureau drawer] (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Practice account books (Albany Business College), 1881 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Practice account books (Albany Business College), undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Practice account books kept by Herbert Nash (Albany Business College), 1881 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Drawings of ships (4 items) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Drawings of ships (5 items) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Drawings of ships (5 items) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Drawings of ships (5 items) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Drawings of ships (5 items) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Drawings of ships (5 items) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Drawings, miscellaneous (5 items) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Drawings, colored (5 items) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Memorabilia: mat made by Leland Stanford, Jr. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Memorabilia: party favor (?) (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Biographical and other papers, 1884-1999; Series 2
  - Clipping re Leland Jr.'s memorial services in California, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Memorials: (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Cook, Mrs. Fannie Bruce, "In Memoriam"
    - Girls' High School, San Francisco, "Poem in Memory of Leland Stanford"
    - Irwin, Will H., "The Picture in the Library," from Sequoia, Sep 18, 1896
    - Newcomer, Prof. A. G., "Memorial Ode," in Sequoia, April 5, 1894
  - Memorials: (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Schuck, Oscar T., "Lines Written in Memory of Leland, Only Child of Ex-Governor and Mrs. Leland Stanford"
    - Smith, Augustine J., "A Picture and a Reflection," originally published in National View, Washington, DC, July 15, 1893
    - Zimmerman, William, "In Memoriam," with cover letter to Mrs. Stanford, 1885 Mar 6, 1885
    - Anonymous, "Thoughts on the Death of a Gifted Son"
  - Memorial tablet in Florence, Italy: typed consular report on unveiling of the tablet on the building where he died, with two photographs; and advertisement from Grand Hotel, 1930, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Leland Stanford, Jr. Museum: booklet and original captions for items displayed (some in Jane L. Stanford's hand), 1886 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Biographical materials: articles and clippings on his toys; genealogical essay; and "The Boy Who Built a College," from Wide Awake, Vol. 34, January 1892 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Memorials (manuscripts and typescripts) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Notes re Stanford mausoleum, and Leland Stanford Jr., monument, 1936, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, biographical: (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Livingston, Louis to Stanford University, re selling pewter soldiers to Leland Jr., and Ray Lyman Wilbur's response, Apr 25, 1943 Apr 27, 1943
    - Postcard of a library with note on verso to Mrs. Stanford re placing Leland Stanford Jr. memorial tablet
  - William T. Ross: telegrams and letter from Mrs. Stanford, 1882 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - William T. Ross: programs and broadsides listing Ross as a speaker, 1868-1877 and undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - William T. Ross: scrapbook of clippings, mostly poetry (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - William T. Ross: miscellaneous papers (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - William T. Ross: miscellaneous correspondence, 1862-1951 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Becca Samson, [memorial poem], Dec 31, 1884; [mss with illuminated "S"] (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - John F. McDonald, "To the Memory of Leland Stanford, Jr.", 1884; [printed on cloth] (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Multiple copies of program from memorial service at Grace Church, Nov 30, 1884 (Box 3)
  - Ada V. Getchell, "Thoughts Suggest by the Early Death and the Beneficent Influences of the Brief Life of Leland Stanford Jr.,", 1885; hand calligraphy and illustrations (Box 4 os)
  - Letter to Jane L. Stanford from Ada V. Getchell, 1886 (Box 4 os)
- Condolence letters and poems sent to Leland and Jane Stanford on the death of Leland Stanford, Jr., 1884-1885; Series 3
  - Cesnola, L. P. di (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Cooper, Sarah (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Lathrop surname (includes Annie Lathrop, Ariel Lathrop, Jeannie Lathrop, and Libbie Lathrop) (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Smith, N. T. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Stanford surname (includes Elijah and Louisa Stanford, Helen Stanford, and Thomas Welton Stanford) (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - A (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Ba-Be (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Bi-Bu (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - C (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - D (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - E-F (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - G (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - H (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - J (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - K-L (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - M (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - O-P (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - R (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Sa-Sl (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Sm-Su (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - T-V (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - W-Y (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Family members (no last name) (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Anonymous (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Incomplete signature (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Illegible signature (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Fragment (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Letter from Lucy to her father describing memorial cross of flowers in Grace Church, San Francisco (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Poems (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Old index to letters (incomplete) (Box 5, Folder 30)